so we invented a third type of cache
which is called the virtually indexed
and physically tagged cache which is
trying to combine the advantages of the
two types of cache it works like this we
start with the virtual address we break
it down into the cache offset index and
tag but we don't use the tag we do use
the index bits from the virtual address
to find the set that we want in the
cache we read the valid bits and the
tags
here but meanwhile we use the page
number from the virtual address to
access the tlb and get the frame number
so now that we got the physical address
we perform the tag check using the
physical address not the virtual one
this is why this is called a virtually
indexed the index bits come from the
virtual address the tag bits come from
the physical address cache and from here
it proceeds normally we know whether we
have a hit and so on so how does this
help note that the cache array and the
tlb axis are proceeding in parallel so
if the tlb is fast enough and usually it
is because it's small the hit time will
be equal to the cach hit time it's
actually the maximum of the two which is
usually the cach hit time so this is
just like the virtual or virtual index
virtually tag cache and we like that we
get the speed advantage of the virtual
caches with this type of cache to do we
need to flush on a context switch well
it turns out no because if we switch the
process so that virtual addresses
correspond to different physical
addresses what we find in the cache will
be checked against the actual physical
address so the virtual address in
another process will map maybe to the
same set but once it Maps there the
actual tag is not going to match because
these two have different tags
so this is like the physical cash and is
nice but what about aliasing recall that
aliasing happens because multiple
virtual addresses in the same address
space might map to the same physical
address but because we do virtual access
to the cache these addresses might end
up in different places in the cache thus
right to one will not be seen by the
other it turns out that there are no
aliasing problems in the virtually index
physically t cach as long as the cach is
small enough and it has to do with where
are the index bits coming from so this
is very very nice because it basically
gives us the correctness the no flush on
Contex switch of the physical cashes
with the heat time of the virtual caches
but let's figure out what do we need to
do in order to not have aliasing